"Are Plant Sterols Safe for Lowering Cholesterol?"
According to an expert
consensus statement
from the European
Atherosclerosis Society,
at the recommended daily intake
of two grams
of plant sterols a day,
the available evidence
does not suggest
any adverse effect associated
with long-term intake.
And evidence from animal
and cell studies suggests
a protective role
of plant sterol intake
and risk of certain cancers.
Human population studies
have also found
a protective effect
of dietary phytosterol intake
on cancer risk;
those who consumed the most
had a 37% lower risk of cancer.
But where are
phytosterols found?
Healthy foods
like nuts and seeds.
Even just a single ounce
of nuts (30 g) a day
is associated
with less cardiovascular risk
and a lower risk of dying
from cancer
and from dying
from all causes put together.
So, phytosterols
may just be a marker
for healthy food intake,
though it's also possible
that phytosterols may be
one of the reasons
nuts and seeds
are so good for us.
There's a new class
of anti-cancer agents
known as histone
deacetylase inhibitors,
available for the low, low cost
of $38,000 a month,
but in terms of the most potent
naturally occurring
such inhibitors
reported to date,
phytosterols may fit the bill,
perhaps one of the reasons
healthy plant foods
are so good for us.
Post-marketing
surveillance studies
are said to have given
phytosterols
a clean bill of health
based on thousands
of consumers,
but the study was done
by the company
that sells those products;
so, I don't take
much comfort from it.
There's a concern
that plant sterols
could reduce the absorption
of certain fat-soluble vitamins.
They don't seem to impact
concentrations of blood levels
of vitamins A, D, or K,
but they can drop
vitamin E levels by about 10%.
The main concern, though,
has been about the loss
of carotenoids
like beta carotene.
One modeling study suggested
that if margarines became
a hundred percent fortified
with phytosterols,
the incidence
of night blindness—
difficulty seeing in dim light—
may increase as much as 19
in a thousand every year,
whereas that would also result
in one in a thousand
not getting heart disease.
Since night blindness
is considered
a relatively minor
visual disturbance,
the benefits of fortification
might clearly outweigh
the putative risk,
but there's no need
to have any risk at all,
because the relatively small
suppression
of plasma carotenoid levels
can be countered
by just eating more fruits
and vegetables.
The problem
with fortifying something
like margarine
with phytosterols
is that people
may cook with it,
and that could cause
the plant sterols to oxidize
into phytosterol
oxidation products.
We know cholesterol oxidation
products are particularly bad,
but we aren't sure
about oxidized phytosterols.
We don't know enough about
what happens when we heat them;
so, better safe than sorry.
Don't cook with
phytosterol-fortified products.
There was
a concerning finding in rats,
where phytosterols
were found to make
their red blood cells
more fragile,
but in mice,
the opposite was found—
their red blood cells
became less fragile,
and in hamsters, there didn't
seem to be any effect.
So, are we more like rats,
mice, or hamsters?
Now, the amount of plant sterols
researchers used in the rats
was, like, 50 times higher
than you'd see in people,
but you really don't know
what normal amounts can do
until you put it to the test,
and it turns out that doesn't
appear to be an issue.
There is, however,
a rare genetic condition
called phytosterolemia,
where people end up
with extremely high levels
of phytosterols in their blood
and end up with horrific
heart disease, even as kids.
But the same mutations
that allow
for the increased absorption
of phytosterols
also allow for the increased
absorption of cholesterol;
so, these unfortunate kids
end up with cholesterol levels
in the 700s.
No wonder they're dying
of heart attacks.
So, when those
who just genetically end up
with higher levels
of phytosterols
in their bloodstream
have higher rates
of cardiovascular disease,
it's not necessarily
because plant sterols
increase the risk
of coronary heart disease,
as some had feared,
but rather because those people
are also sucking up
extra regular cholesterol.
These genetic variations
in sterol transporters,
result in increased blood levels
of phytosterols,
increased intestinal
cholesterol absorption
and subsequently result
in higher LDL.
In fact, that's how we estimate
how good people are
at absorbing cholesterol,
by just seeing
how many plant sterols
they have in their blood.
So, people with lots
of phytosterols in their blood
also have markedly elevated
LDL cholesterol.
No wonder they're at risk
for heart disease.
However, this increase
in cholesterol absorption
doesn't fully explain
the increased risk;
so, it's possible
that phytosterols
may indeed contribute
directly to heart disease,
raising questions
about the safety
of supplementing food
with phytosterols
for the purpose of
cardiovascular risk reduction.
But the risk in LDL
achieved by the consumption
of phytosterol-enriched foods
is 20 to 40 times greater
than the increase
in phytosterols in the blood.
Thus, phytosterols would need
to cause 20 to 40 times
more atherosclerosis
than cholesterol
to cancel out
their positive effect
on cholesterol reduction.
Yet, there is
no apparent evidence for this.
In fact, at the levels
we get in our blood
from consuming a few grams
of plant sterols a day,
there is no association
with cardiovascular events
in population studies.
So, that's how you get
these assurances
that phytosterols are safe.